Finding Aid for Mabel E. Rugen Papers 1921-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mabel E. Rugen Papers 1921-1989, 1930-1970
Rugen, Mabel E.
15 linear feet
Professor of physical education for women in the School of Education and professor of health education in the School of Public Health at the University of Michigan. Series in the collection include: biographical information, correspondence, research papers, health education projects and studies, University of Michigan School of Education, University of Michigan School of Public Health, course materials, associations files, and topical files; includes photographs.
93807 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mabel E. Rugen (donor 8043 ) in June 1992.
The collection is open for research.
Mabel E. Rugen was born May 13, 1902, in Glenview, Illinois. After receiving her B.S. in physical education from the University of Wisconsin in 1925, she worked as a physical education teacher in the Glenview Public Schools. She then went on to New York where she earned a M.A. (1929) and a Ph.D. (1931) from New York University in physical education.
Rugen first taught health, physical education and biology in the elementary and secondary schools of Kansas, New York and New Jersey. In 1930, she secured a position at the University of Michigan as Assistant Professor of Physical Education for Women. Soon after, she was promoted to Associate Professor of Physical Education and Health Coordinator for the University High School (both appointments were in the School of Education). As associate professor, Rugen taught student teachers in the directed teaching program for physical education. In 1941, she joined the faculty of the newly formed School of Public Health as Assistant Professor of Health Education, while retaining her position at the School of Education. In 1946 she was promoted to full Professor of Health Education in both the School of Education and the School of Public Health. Rugen held this joint appointment until her retirement in 1970.
Rugen's primary focus during her years at the university was teaching. During her long career she taught both undergraduate and graduate students and directed many masters theses and doctoral dissertations. Rugen played an active part in the development of guidelines and requirements for both undergraduate and graduate programs.
During her tenure at the university, Rugen also became actively involved with state projects that sought to monitor and improve the health of both children and adults. Her leadership in organizations such as the Michigan Joint Committee on Health Education and the Michigan Curriculum Program in the 1930s made her a nationally known figure in the field of public health. The Community Health Service Project (CHSP) (1942-1946), in which Rugen was involved from its beginning, provided instruction in health education to high school students. The CHSP sought to provide basic health skills primarily to high school women in the hopes that they might choose to become nurses.
Mabel E. Rugen belonged to more than twenty local and national organizations and is the author of over ninety articles, book chapters and brochures relating to the fields of physical education and public health.
The Mabel E. Rugen Papers contain a wealth of information which documents the early years of the University of Michigan's physical education program for women, professional education for teachers of physical education, and the important contributions Rugen made in a field previously dominated by men. The collection has been divided intellectually into eight main series: Correspondence, Research Papers, Health Education Projects and Studies, School of Education, School of Public Health, Course Materials, Associations, and Topical.
Subjects:
Community Health Service Project.; Michigan Curriculum Study.; Michigan Joint Committee on Health Education.; Michigan League for Nursing.; Rugen, Mabel E.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physical Education for Women.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Children.; Community Health Service Project.; Health care.; Infants.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Public health--Michigan.; Rugen, Mabel E.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  - Professional biography, lists of publications, and news clippings (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (1.5 linear ft.; 1930-1980) contains both personal and general correspondence relating to the multitude of people and projects with which Rugen was actively involved both within and without the University of Michigan. Correspondence relating to Rugen's appointment to Michigan in 1930 shows her enthusiasm and conviction about teaching and documents an early interest in developing a health education program at Michigan. The general correspondence sub-series includes a sampling of Rugen's correspondence with faculty, students, and organizations, which Rugen chose to combine in one alphabetical sequence. Correspondence has also been filed by the originating school, organization, etc.
  - Appointment to Michigan 1930 (Box 1)
  - Health Education Alumni 1961-1980 (Box 1)
  - Personal
    - 1930-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1964-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - UCLA 1971 (Box 1)
  - General 1950s, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - General 1950s, 9 folders (Box 2)
- Research Papers
  Research Papers (0.25 linear ft.; 1921-1960) contains an assortment of important papers from various aspects of her career. Worth noting is a draft of her Ph.D. dissertation which illuminates her early theories of the teaching of health and physical education in grade schools. Also included are various papers presented at conferences throughout her career and some early essays on her childhood in Glenview.
  - High School Papers 1921 (Box 2)
  - Conference Papers 1930s-1960s (Box 2)
  - Doctoral Dissertation 1930 (Box 2)
  - Health Tests and Measurements in Education. 1929 (Box 2)
  - Health Tests 1930s (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Public Health Appraisal 1929 (Box 2)
- Health Education Projects and Studies
  Health Education Projects and Studies (1.5 linear ft.; 1921-1962) contains material relating to several important projects that Rugen worked on during the 1930s-1940s. Papers documenting the Community Health Service Project, Joint Committee on Health Education and the Michigan Curriculum Study reflect the growing interest in public health due, in part, to the findings of the draft board on the poor health of soldiers examined during conscription for World War II and the shortage of nurses and doctors due to the war. Many photographs are included which document the educational classes which taught public health during the Community Health Service Project of 1942-1946. Both the Joint Committee on Health Education and the Michigan Curriculum Study were primarily concerned with formalizing public health education in Michigan. Rugen was an active member of many sub-committees of these projects which cover topics such as sex education, temperance education, and teacher education. The Michigan League for Nursing materials document a Nurse Recruitment Study for which Rugen directed the study and wrote the final report in her capacity as Chairman of the Subcommittee on Evaluation of the Committee on Careers.
  - Community Health Service Project 1942-1946
    - Background Materials (Box 2)
    - Agendas and Minutes (Box 2)
    - Case Studies (examples from Michigan schools) (Box 2)
    - Community Health Service Course
      - Background Materials (Box 2)
      - Original Manual (Box 2)
      - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Comparative Projects & Conferences with State Supported Institutions of Higher Education (Box 3)
    - Evaluation (of C.H.S.P.) (Box 3)
    - Health Education Conference with College Representatives (Box 3)
    - Informal Conference with Representatives of National Nursing Agencies (Box 3)
    - Instructional Aids Available to Schools (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 3)
    - Narrative Reports (Box 3)
    - Plans for Cooperation with State Schools (Box 3)
    - Publicity (Box 3)
    - Suggested Outline August 1944 (Box 3)
    - Summary Reports on Schools Participating (Box 3)
    - Teacher Education (Box 3)
  - Joint Committee on Health Education 1921-1938
    - Background Materials (Box 3)
    - Committee on health Education in Schools, Minutes 1936-1938 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1935-1953 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1936-1938 (Box 3)
    - Sub-committee on School Health Education
      - Health Education Projects 1935-1936, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan Curriculum Study 1938-1962
    - Background Materials (Box 3)
    - Committee on Health Education
      - Minutes and Agenda 1939-1948 (Box 3)
      - Reports 1942-1948 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Basic Factual Material for Teachers 1940 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on County Institutes 1940-1941 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Educational Implications of Health Service Activities 1940-1941 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Health Education in Secondary Schools 1940-1942 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Physical Education 1940-1943 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Safety Education 1939-1944 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Sex Education 1938-1940, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Teacher Education 1938-1941 (Box 3)
      - Sub-committee on Temperance Education 1940-1956 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Nutrition and the Schools 1943-1945 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1938-1946 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Consultants 1939-1940 (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Steering Committee
      - Committee on Application of Research Findings 1942-1943 (Box 4)
      - Minutes 1939-1963 (Box 4)
    - Exploratory Committee on Health Education 1939 (Box 4)
    - Town & Country Administrative Roundtable
      - Health Survey 1944-1945, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Participating Schools 1943-1944 (Box 4)
  - Michigan League for Nursing 1954-1956
    - Nurse Recruitment Study
      - Background Materials (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Final Report (Box 4)
      - Minutes (Box 4)
- School of Education
  School of Education materials (1.75 linear ft.; 1930-1957) are divided into two subseries: Correspondence and a Topical File.
  - Correspondence (Sample) 1930s-1940s
    The correspondence file is a sample of the original correspondence file included to document the range of correspondence Rugen saved, including routine periodical and film orders, thank you notes, and correspondence with students. The sample file is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent or by name of agency and covers primarily the 1930s and 1940s.
    - Allen, Ross (Box 4)
    - B (Box 4)
    - Bartley, Lua (Box 4)
    - C (Box 4)
    - Cragg, Nadine (Box 4)
    - Crogen, Corinne (Box 4)
    - Deach, Dorothy (Box 4)
    - Edmonson, James B. (Dean) (Box 4)
    - Elliott, Eugene B. (Box 4)
    - G (Box 4)
    - HA-HE (Box 4)
    - HI-HU (Box 4)
    - J (Box 4)
    - K (Box 4)
    - Koopman, G. Robert (Box 4)
    - L (Box 4)
    - Mc (Box 4)
    - MA-ME (Box 4)
    - MI-MO (Box 5)
    - Mitchell, Elmer D. (Box 5)
    - N (Box 5)
    - O (Box 5)
    - P (Box 5)
    - R (Box 5)
    - S (Box 5)
    - Strachan, Louise (Box 5)
    - T (Box 5)
    - Thompson, A.W. (Box 5)
  - Topical File
    The Topical File subseries contains materials arranged alphabetically by department or topic. Most of this material also covers primarily the 1930s-1940s. The Physical Education materials include meeting minutes, correspondence and miscellaneous data regarding women's physical education. Materials (especially lesson plans and teaching manuals) from the University High School where Rugen directed student teachers in the teaching of physical education for both junior high and high school students document progressive teaching techniques from the 1930s.
    - Bureau of School Services (Box 5)
    - Coordinated Workshops 1940 (Box 5)
    - Dept. F (Physical Education, Athletics, and School Health)
      - Miscellaneous 1933-1949, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Integrated Workshops 1944 (Box 5)
    - Physical Education
      - Correspondence 1930s (Box 5)
      - Doctoral Preliminary Examination 1930s-1940s (Box 5)
      - Graduate Programs 1931-1948 (Box 5)
      - Majors 1930s-1940s (Box 5)
      - Minutes 1941-1946 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous 1930s (Box 5)
      - Requirements 1932-1940 (Box 5)
    - Progressive Curriculum Development 1937 (Box 5)
    - Sub-committee on General Education Requirements 1954-1961 (Box 5)
    - Summer Education Conference "Health as an Ideal" 1955 (Box 5)
    - University High School
      - Directed Teaching
        - Lesson Plans 1931 (Box 5)
        - Miscellaneous 1930s (Box 5)
        - Notes, Bulletins, Agenda 1930-1931 (Box 5)
        - Physical Education Introductory Material 1932-1938 (Box 5)
        - Self-evaluations 1930-1932, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Health Related Statistics 1946-1948 (Box 5)
      - Record Forms (Box 6)
      - Reports & Bulletins 1930-1957 (Box 6)
- School of Public Health
  School of Public Health materials (3.25 linear ft.; 1940-1970) have also been divided into two subseries: Correspondence and a Topical File. The Correspondence File is a sample of the original correspondence file maintained to document the range of correspondence that Rugen saved. The sample file is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent or by name of agency.
  - Correspondence (Sample)
    The Correspondence File is a sample of the original correspondence file maintained to document the range of correspondence that Rugen saved. The sample file is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent or by name of agency.
    - A 1960s (Box 6)
    - Allen, Ross L. 1940s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Armstrong, Mary P. 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Atwater, Reginald M. 1940s-1950s (Box 6)
    - Beeuwkes, Adelia M. 1940s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Bell, Margaret (Dr.) 1940s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Boatman, Ralph 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Bowman, Robert A. 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Edmonson, James B. (Dean) 1930s-1950s (Box 6)
    - Grout, Ruth 1940s-1960s (Box 6)
    - H 1950s-1970s (Box 6)
    - Heller, Irene 1960s (Box 6)
    - Martikainen, Helen A. 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
    - Mytinger, Robert 1950s (Box 6)
    - Oed, Minnie K. 1950s-1960s (Box 6)
    - R 1960s (Box 6)
    - Smith, Donald (Dr.) 1960s, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Stacey, Dorothy J. 1950s-1960s, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Sundwall, John (Dean) 1950s (Box 6)
    - Wegman, Myron 1960s, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Vaughan, Henry F. (Dean) 1950s-1960s, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Yoho, Robert 1950s-1960s (Box 7)
  - Topical File
    The Topical File contains material arranged by department or topic. Included are the Reports of the Health Education Program which outline the policy and program changes in public health education between 1949-1969. Other administration documents such as minutes and annual reports trace the development of the School of Public Health's Dept. of Health Education and the active role which Mabel Rugen played. Materials on the increasingly important role of field experience as part of public health education also deserve special attention.
    - Citizens Public Health Conference March 25-26, 1953 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Instruction
      - Agenda 1954-1959 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1955-1963 (Box 7)
      - Memoranda 1954-1960 (Box 7)
      - Minutes 1954-1959 (Box 7)
      - Reports 1954-1960 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Social Research 1949-1950 (Box 7)
    - Conference on Teaching of Accident Prevention in Schools of Public Health (Box 7)
    - Continuing Education Service
      - Seminar on Health Education in Cancer Control
        - Project Advisory Committee 1966-1967, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Discussion Materials May 7-12, 1967 (Box 7)
    - Dept. of Community Health Services 1962 (Box 7)
    - Dept. of Health Development
      - Annual Reports 1963-1968, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1967-1969 (Box 7)
      - Executive Committee, Minutes 1964-1969, 7 folders (Box 7)
      - Minutes 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Policies 1962-1968 (Box 7)
      - Program Advisors, Minutes 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Family Living/Sex Education
      - Committee on Family Life Education 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Governors Task Force on University and Family Life Education 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      - Health Education and Family Living Workshop 1950 (Box 8)
      - India Family Planing Team 1963-1964 (Box 8)
      - Program on Family Living 1949-1954 (Box 8)
      - School Nursing, Family Living and Health Education, Summer 1955 (Box 8)
      - Sex/Family Life Education 1951-1956 (Box 8)
    - Field Experience
      - Committee on Field Experience 1962-1967, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Conferences
        - Conference on Field Education for Health Educators and Public Health Dentists April 3-4, 1964 (Box 8)
        - Health Educator's Conference on Field Experience May 31-June 1, 1962 (Box 8)
      - Field Training Materials
        - 1949-1961 (Box 8)
        - 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Health Education Faculty Meetings 1962-1969, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Health Education Steering Committee 1965 (Box 8)
    - Health Education Institute September 20-22, 1962 (Box 8)
    - Inservice Training Course July, 1947
      - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
      - Proceedings (Box 8)
    - Migrant Health Education Project 1964-1965 (Box 8)
    - Report of the Health Education Program 1949-1969, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Summer Session Course Offerings 1954-1969 (Box 9)
    - Teacher Education 1951-1960 (Box 9)
- Course Materials
  Course Materials (3 linear ft.; 1930-1969) contain syllabi, course handouts, lecture notes, final exams, quizzes and some student evaluations which highlight the importance of Rugen's forty years of teaching both public health and education students. Because of changing course numbers, this material is arranged by the course name. After the course name various course numbers are listed which reflect numbers assigned to the course by either the School of Education or the School of Public Health.
  - Lecture Notes (course unknown) 1950, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Adult Education, B182
    - Course Handouts 1940s (Box 9)
    - Lecture Notes 1939-1948 (Box 9)
    - Syllabi and Exams 1938-1943 (Box 9)
  - Community Health Education PHP270 1942-1952 (Box 9)
  - Community Organization for Health Education HD640 1961-1968 (Box 9)
  - Curriculum Problems in Physical Education F213 1939-1948 (Box 9)
  - Directed Teaching in Physical Education, F100e/D100
    - Course Handouts 1930s (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous 1930s (Box 9)
    - Workbook for Student Teachers 1930s (Box 9)
  - Education in the United States, A10
    - Course Notes 1942-1946, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Syllabi & Course Handouts 1940s (Box 9)
  - Elementary and Secondary School Programs, F45/F46 1936-1941, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Elementary Games, F41
    - Miscellaneous 1930s (Box 10)
    - Progressive Games Party undated (Box 10)
  - Elementary School Curriculum B105 undated (Box 10)
  - Elementary School Programs F44 1942 (Box 10)
  - Field Experience in Health Education, HD740
    - Miscellaneous 1950s (Box 10)
    - 1967;1969, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - First Aid Course 1942-1943 (Box 10)
  - Fundamentals 1929-1930 (Box 10)
  - Games Materials F47 undated (Box 10)
  - Health and Human Development HD501 1961 (Box 10)
  - Health Aspects of the School Curriculum B546 1962-1963 (Box 10)
  - Health Aspects of the School Curriculum / Special Programs in Health Education B170/PHP170 1949-1955 (Box 10)
  - Health Education Foundations, HD542/HD543
    - Fall 1966-Winter 1967 (Box 10)
    - Fall 1968-Winter 1969 (Box 10)
  - Health Education Methods for Public Health Workers HD541/PHP277 1961-1963 (Box 10)
  - Introduction to Community Health Education PHP174 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - Introduction to Health Education, PHP172/HD440
    - Class Handouts 1945-1961, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Introduction to Tests and Measurements in Physical Education, F118
    - Class Handouts & Exams 1935-1943 (Box 10)
    - Lecture Notes 1942-1943 (Box 10)
  - Materials in School Health Education, PHP271/HD545
    - Course Evaluations 1958-1961, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Course Handouts 1953-1968 (Box 10)
    - Exams 1942-1969 (Box 10)
  - Methods and Materials in Adult Health Education Hygiene 228 1939-1940 (Box 11)
  - Methods and Materials in Community Health Education PHP172 1940-1947 (Box 11)
  - Methods and Materials in Health Education, F115/FG115
    - Course Handouts 1930s, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Extension Division, Hillsdale 1934-1935 (Box 11)
    - Lecture Notes 1931-1938 (Box 11)
  - Methods and Materials in Physical Education for Elementary Schools F42/F45 1942-1943 (Box 11)
  - Methods of Instruction and Supervision of Physical Education F212/F43 1933-1937 (Box 11)
  - Organization and Administration of Physical Education, F11b
    - Class Materials 1930-1931 (Box 11)
    - Directory of Physical Education Materials 1931-1934 (Box 11)
    - Lecture Notes 1931 (Box 11)
  - Problems in the Teaching of School Health D271 1948-1952 (Box 11)
  - Public Health Education Hygiene 210 1940-1941 (Box 11)
  - School Health Education Programs, HD645/PHP272
    - Topical
      - Final Exams 1950s (Box 11)
      - Syllabi & Units I and II 1950-1960 (Box 11)
      - Units III and IV 1950-1960 (Box 11)
    - Chronological
      - 1955-1958, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - 1964/65 (Box 11)
      - 1965, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - 1968 (Box 11)
  - School Health Problems F9/Hygiene 107 1930s-1940s (Box 11)
  - Seminar in Health Education PHP276/D273/HD649 1960s, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Seminar in Physical Education & Recreation F215a 1940s (Box 12)
  - Seminar in School Health Education (Masters Level) D773 1957-1963 (Box 12)
  - Seminar on Population Planning HD875 1965 (Box 12)
  - Supervision of Secondary School Subjects B156 1933-1936 (Box 12)
  - The Teacher and the School B75 1949-1950 (Box 12)
  - Teaching of School Health, D173/D473
    - Course Handouts 1966-1968 (Box 12)
    - Exams 1964-1969 (Box 12)
    - Section 2: Dental Hygienists 1964-1969 (Box 12)
- Associations
  Associations material (2 linear ft.; 1931-1976) is arranged alphabetically by name of association. This series shows the depth of Rugen's involvement in the field of public health. Rugen was active in more than twenty regional and national associations covering the fields of public health and physical education, her papers trace the development of some organizations (e.g. SOPHE and the American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation) from their beginnings and highlight Rugen's tremendous commitment to the field of public health.
  - American Academy of Physical Education 1946-1981, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - American Association for Health and Physical Education 1935-1940 (Box 12)
  - American Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation 1931-1950, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - American Medical Association 1963-1969 (Box 12)
  - American National Council for Health Education of the Public, Inc. 1961-1964 (Box 12)
  - American Public Health Association 1973-1975 (Box 12)
  - American Physical Education Association Committee on Promotion 1936-1938 (Box 13)
  - American School Health Association 1962-1981 (Box 13)
  - Anna Botsford Bach Home 1970-1985 (Box 13)
  - Association for the Study of Community Organization 1953-1965 (Box 13)
  - Association of Schools of Public Health 1950s-1960s, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Committee on Assessing the Progress of Education 1969 (Box 13)
  - Metropolitan Detroit Bureau of Cooperative School Studies School Health Committee Minutes 1949-1962, 4 folders (Box 13)